<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:id="Hunt_mssRC481" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>California</region>
                  <settlement></settlement>
                  <institution>Huntington Library</institution>
                  <repository></repository>
                  <collection>Carlile Papers</collection>
                  <idno>RC 481</idno>
                  <msName></msName>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <author></author>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="prsn" 
               matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " 
               replacementPattern="https://github.com/Cantablet/Radical-Britain/blob/master/references/people/personography.xml#$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="isni" 
               matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " 
               replacementPattern="http://isni.org/isni/$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="viaf" 
               matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " 
               replacementPattern="https://viaf.org/viaf/$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="plc" 
               matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " 
               replacementPattern="https://github.com/Cantablet/Radical-Britain/blob/master/references/places/placeography.xml#$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tgn" 
               matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " 
               replacementPattern="http://vocab.getty.edu/page/tgn/$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="grp" 
               matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " 
               replacementPattern="https://github.com/Cantablet/Radical-Britain/blob/master/references/groups/groupography.xml#$1">
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="prsn:Carl01">
                  <forename><supplied reason="omitted-in-original">Richard</supplied></forename>
                  <surname><supplied reason="omitted-in-original">Carlile</supplied></surname>
               </persName>
               <orgName></orgName>
               <placeName ref="plc:Enfi01">Enfield High Way</placeName>
               <date when="1839-12-22"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="prsn:Turt01">
                  <forename><supplied reason="omitted-in-original">Thomas</supplied></forename>
                  <surname><supplied reason="omitted-in-original">Turton</supplied></surname>
               </persName>
               <orgName></orgName>
               <placeName ref="tgn"></placeName>
               <date></date>
            </correspAction>            
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>My Dear Friend,</p>
         <p>Just as I received your letter last monday, I was going off to London with <persName ref="prsn:Shar01">Mrs. C.</persName> to her Lecture. It was a failure as to profit, even as to expences : which may be partly attributed to want of advertisement ; the proprietor of the Hall undertaking and neglecting to advertise it in two or three newspapers. We go again to morrow : and if there be no improvement I shall see then necessity of separating myself entirely from all places in which the Socialists figure. to me they are an opposing sect, and I find it unwise to be mixed up with the prejudices peculiarly surrounding the. They will flourish as a sect for a few years ; but they are now, I learnt at Birmingham, much cramped for want of funds. Tytherly will be their tether. their little warfare with superstition excepted, I cannot see them other than a very contemptible sect, as much so as any religious sect.</p>
            <p>I have delayed sending you this parcel a few days that I may enclose you my letter to Hugh Stowell, in which I bespeak your interest. the Register is all but a death struggle. I cannot swear for its living from week to week. it has no fair play any where. I am aiming at a shop of my own as a place of publication ; but fear some difficulty in getting a suitable pleasing place. London Winter and Death to me are  synonymous. I feel a death every day I spend there and come home pitiably [[2]] ill : and what is as strange, that after being home twenty four hours I recover and breathe easily. It is the walking in London that distresses me. Here with a good fire no one can feel less pain and distress than myself. I do not despair of passing a few more useful years, though I am greatly bothered for money to live with. I can tell you for your satisfaction, though I do not wish it to go beyond you, that Mr Prout sent me a note to request I would call on him. I called on tuesday but he was at his country house. his partner told me the errand, that Mr P. had my name on his will ; but thinking I was not likely to want more hereafter than now had resolved to give me that benefit while he was living : and purposes to see if he cannot combine a few town and country friends to subscribe me a hundred pounds a year for life. he and Mr Place[?] made an effort to do this while I was in Dorchester Gaol but it failed, and I fear it will fail now. Money is more readily subscribed to pompous charity than to private support. About the year 1823, they could only muster eleven subscribers of sovereigns annually. hHowever I am to see him on tuesday if possible.</p>
            <p>Cosmopolite's first letter in the Iris had some errors of which the Printer's Reader should have been ashamed. the second letter was correct and good. Mr Levison gave me a hint that the Woods are not overstocked with generosity, in saying, they would not part with money for any thing. if I can put my hand on them, I will send you two of Neville [[3]] Wood's Letters to me. I have now as little desire to be introduced to them, as I had a strong one when at Sheffield. Charles Waterton, though a very narrow minded Roman Catholic, met me and welcomed me to his house in better style : though of course, he wished me to become a Roman Catholic, beyond which he has not an idea, natural history of birds excepted.</p>
            <p>I have now packed up going of necessity for waste paper four thousand sheets of the Isis, every one of which contains either a good philosophical discourse or something as good. what would it be for a gentleman with a little money to scatter these gratuitously? it grieves me, so to part with them, when I see a people stupid for want of such reading. they will not fetch me above 5£. the paper cost 15£ besides the print. this is a specimen of my money grubbing. it is Hetherington who calls me a money grubber. he is about to trade in bankruptcy again. he sent back all his usual No of Register for my notice of him last week, would not sell or send one into the country. I have sent you 2 Vols. of the Isis as near as I can make them perfect. you may pick up the two or three intermediate Nos in Sheffield. I also send one perfect vol. of the Gauntlet, as I have four remaining. Part 4 of Freemasonry is not yet printed. that lies with Mr Cunningham, as he gave me ten pounds for wedding it a year and [a] half ago. – I parted with five thousand sheets of the Moralist as waste paper in the spring and lately 400 of Smith's Speculative Dictionary.</p>
            <p>I have the Clock safe through Holmes, whom I met the other day in London.</p> 
            <p>[[4]] I shall be rather sorry if you have destroyed Watson's Letters to John Coates ; because I know, if he were accused of writing such letters, he would deny it. I was astounded at the infamy of the letters ; for I assure you that while I had any control over the Rotunda, it was no more like a brothel than any other or the best private house in London. I wanted these letters as a case. I know there has been an undercurrent of calumnious report of this kind. I have traced it to Cleave[?] Watson and Hetherington l but these were the first written documents I fixed on. it is the knowledge of this undercurrent of calumny that induces me to repeat the challenge so often to any of these fellows to say any thing openly.</p>
            <p>I have not received any Regenerator this week, so I expect it is dead. Tom would rise above the Chartists , if he could live above them. I have been rather pleased with the vigorous style of his writing. he has done what I could not do at his age ; to be sure he has been brought up in it. his marriage is a direful drag to him. there is already a child. – I am not surprised at what you say of Lingard. I saw all was going wrong.</p>
            <p>The only thing I want that I left with you in Sheffield is the bundle of pens l but this is a trifle. I mention it only in joke. the Portmanteau was worn out. I do not forget that I promised you Julian Hibbert's Iron Bed Stead. when it moves, you shall have it. it is fixed at present in my little study and may be useful.</p>
            <p>Macconnell wants me to attempt with him the getting up of a Discussion Society, a sort of Form. I dare say we shall attempt something of the kind. I opposed him on the precedence of Universal Suffrage last tuesday week at Theobold's Road. he is a tart, talented, practical speaker, formerly a Dissenting Minister ; but I look upon him altogether as a marketable man.</p>
            <p>I am well stocked in Books for reading this inter, having Plato, Cudworth, Chevalier Ramsay &amp;c. I have just got through Suetonius, Heroclian, Ramsay and Plato's Republic.</p> 
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
