<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>California</region>
                  <settlement/>
                  <institution>Huntington Library</institution>
                  <repository/>
                  <collection>Carlile Papers</collection>
                  <idno>mssRC 460</idno>
                  <msName/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <author/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="prsn" matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " replacementPattern="https://github.com/Cantablet/Radical-Britain/blob/master/references/people/personography.xml#$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="isni" matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " replacementPattern="http://isni.org/isni/$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="viaf" matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " replacementPattern="https://viaf.org/viaf/$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="plc" matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " replacementPattern="https://github.com/Cantablet/Radical-Britain/blob/master/references/places/placeography.xml#$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tgn" matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " replacementPattern="http://vocab.getty.edu/page/tgn/$1">
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="grp" matchPattern=" ([a-z]+) " replacementPattern="https://github.com/Cantablet/Radical-Britain/blob/master/references/groups/groupography.xml#$1">
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="prsn:Carl01">
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname>Carlile</surname>
               </persName>
               <orgName/>
               <placeName ref="tgn:7010477">Manchester</placeName>
               <date when="1837-12-08"/>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="prsn:Turt01">
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname>Turton</surname>
               </persName>
               <orgName/>
               <placeName ref="tgn:7010692"><supplied>Sheffield</supplied></placeName>
               <date/>
            </correspAction>            
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p><choice><abbr>Dr</abbr><expan>Dear</expan></choice> Sir,</p>
         <p>I have a commission for you. My valuable friends in <placeName ref="tgn:7008132">Gloucestershire</placeName><note>The Cheltenham ladies</note> write me thus:— "A
            Philanthropist of one genus puts me in mind of one of another order, <persName ref="prsn:Robe01">Samuel Roberts</persName>, of <placeName ref="tgn:7010692">Sheffield</placeName> I believe, his printer is <persName ref="Blac01">J. Blackwell</persName>, <placeName ref="tgn:7010692">Sheffield</placeName>.— This Good Man is truly
            interested in ameliorating the hard lot of Chimney Sweeping Boys and also of Gipsies.— I
            have tried ineffectually to get his publications which I particularly wanted to lend to
            a young clergyman whose feelings of humanity appeared to be sincerely developing towards
            the former class of unfortunate ill used begins, and I would fair have fostered this
            valuable opening in his mind by lending him S. Roberts' work on the subject containing
            prose and poetry; but the Bookseller in London said it was out of print."</p>
         <p>If you can pick me up this work in <placeName ref="tgn:7010692">Sheffield</placeName>, pray do so, and if the price be not large,
            a dozen copies will be preferable to one. My friends are very lavish in their gift of
            useful books. And as to supplying me with money, they have made me rich! Their
            remittances already amount to two hundred pounds. I shall be sending you a parcel [[2]]
            before I got to <placeName ref="tgn:7011781">London</placeName> and will remit the price of the Books and any thing you will say
            is due to yourself or <persName ref="prsn:Otle01">Mr Otley</persName>. <persName ref="prsn:Shar01">Mrs C.</persName> and I are to go and visit these ladies before I
            return to Lancashire.— <persName ref="prsn:Carl02">Tom Paine</persName> is here and will remain. If you will let <persName ref="prsn:Turt02">T.T. <choice><abbr>Junr</abbr><expan>Junior</expan></choice></persName>
            come and spend his Christmas with him ; we can accommodate him well in my absence and my
            Chapel is already engaged for the Christmas Bells. I shall want him as a preacher by and
            bye : as you will see by an advertisement I am to send you. We are staying with <persName ref="prsn:Camp01">Mr Campion</persName>, <placeName ref="plc:Manc02">44 Booth Street, Oxford Road</placeName>, my old shopman.</p>
         <p>I sent you a parcel lately with some tracts of mine and some <persName ref="prsn:Shep01"></persName>Shepherd. I can send more
            Shepherd if you can make a pleasure in circulating them.</p>
         <p>I shall leave <placeName ref="tgn:7010477">Manchester</placeName> for three weeks about the 20th Inst and wish to hear from you
            before that time. this is my 47th birthday. With care in the Winter, I think I shall
            wear a dozen years longer: but I must take care. <placeName ref="tgn:7008171">Yorkshire</placeName> air suits me better than
            <placeName ref="tgn:7010477">Manchester</placeName>.</p>
         <p>[3]] <persName ref="prsn:Shar01">Mrs C</persName> will return with me and lecture here and about ; and a trial will be made
            whether or not she has taken for a public life. I have never heard her lecture but once,
            that was to a small audience ; therefore I am no judge: but I mark that she has no study
            in philosophical matters; and on that I think much depends. I shall help on that head as
            I did in the Isis; but the feeling and originality is superior to the mechanical
            delivery of sentiment.</p> 
         <p><persName ref="prsn:Carl02">Tom Paine</persName> is likely to start here as a Bookseller. I must do as I did in 1820, run a
            new agency through the country: for I shall be bringing out a new class of books. There
            is no liken between me and the Radicals.</p>
         <p>I am putting the Socialists to their tether on the Monday evening. It is astonishing how
            ill men bear discussion. These Socialists are as offensive and dishonest as any
            religious sect when brought to discussion. I find the same outcry against the Penny
            Admission here as there was about a shilling and sixpence at <placeName ref="tgn:7010692">Sheffield</placeName>.</p> 
         <p>Love to all your family. </p>
         <p>Respectfully richard carlile</p>
         
         <p>[[4]] PS I kept my letter open until <persName ref="prsn:Carl02">Tom </persName> returned from the Town, thinking that by
            possibility, I might hear from you. Sure enough I have. The Box is at <persName ref="prsn:Heyw01">Mr Heywood's</persName> and I
            dare say all is right.</p> 
         <p>As soon as my discussion with <persName ref="prsn:Gree01">Green</persName> is ready, you shall have a parcel back.</p>
         <p>I fancied I saw how things were going at <placeName ref="tgn:7010692">Sheffield</placeName>. I am not surprised at it. Frivolity
            seems more suited to the present state of the human mind than any sound, serious and
            permanent principle. notwithstanding, I feel myself right enough for the future: and
            rejoice in the course I have taken.</p> 
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
